## MONICA CATHERINE PUSHPA

Somerset, NJ 08873 • <u>monicapushpa@gmail.com</u> • 91-96634 66558 (India) https://www.linkedin.com/in/monica-catherine-pushpa/

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Southern California, Marshall School of Business – Los Angeles, CA

August 2020

Master of Business Administration (M.B.A.)

 ${\bf Bharathidas an\ University}-{\bf India}$ 

May 2004

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.) in Computer Science and Engineering

#### **SUMMARY**

Seasoned technology leader with 12+ years of global, cross-functional experience in business analysis, program and Agile project management . I am currently seeking a role where I can best utilize my Engineering background and my MBA skillset to deliver value to the customer.

#### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

Certifications – Certified ScrumMaster®, Certified Scrum Product Owner® from SCRUM ALLIANCE®, AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner

**Business Analysis** – Value Stream/Process Mapping, Root Cause Analysis, Business Case, Use Case, As-Is & Future State Maps, Fit-Gap Analysis, Business Process Improvements, Scenario Modeling, Data Analytics using SQL, R, Tableau, Data Processing with Hadoop/Java, Process automation using Camunda and MS Visio

**Requirements/ Documentation Management** – System Requirements Specifications (SRS), URS, BRD, PRD, MRD, Install & Process Guides, Online Help, Programmer References, User Story Writing, Journey Mapping. **Tools**- MS Office, Visio, Madcap Flare, RoboHelp, IBM DOORS, Rational ClearQuest & ClearCase.

**Program/Release Management** – Project Scoping, Dashboards/Reporting, QA Support, Change Management, Drive and co-ordinate Release Roadmap including Design, Analysis, Coding, Unit/ Integration Testing, UAT, Deployment Scheduling, and Production Readiness. **Tools Used** - Jira, Rally, Confluence, GitHub, VSS.

**Agile Product Development** – Prototyping, UX/Design, Market Research, Customer Segmentation, Product-Market Fitment, Technology Strategy & Roadmaps, Backlog Grooming & Prioritization, Sprint & Release Planning.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Virtusa Corporation** – Los Angeles, CA / Clinton, NJ/ Chennai, India Program Manager, Business Consulting

Mar 2021 – April 2023

- Developed program charter and high-level project plans after understanding the foundation of org strategy and worked with stakeholders to find alignment with roadmap targets/release processes.
- Co-ordinated with interdependent teams for charting out release strategy and collaborated with QA on finalizing a comprehensive test case list for UAT and finally get signed off by stakeholders.
- Managed end-to-end planning, scoping, scheduling, budgeting, sourcing and coordination for large-scale transformation programs based on Waterfall and Scrum/Agile frameworks.
- Managed range of activities for Change Management (CAB) Advisory to get approvals for production releases, set up post-prod verification calls with consumers and complete handover to support team.
- Tracked key performance metrics such as team velocity, cycle time, sprint burndown, defect density, and scope creep for wealth management portfolio products and applications. Dashboard reporting in Jira.
- Facilitated and hosted Scrum of Scrums, Sprint Planning, Story Mapping, Daily Standups, Refinement, Review/ Retrospectives; cascaded program-level changes and ensured teams are on the same page.
- Proactively identified and removed roadblocks for cross-functional team of developers, analysts, DevOps, and QA by collaborating with broader scrum teams and external resources.
- Anticipated Governance, Risk, and Compliance (GRC) worklist items and proactively addressed issues to ensure mitigation planning and change control. Owned GRC weekly reporting to PMO head.

Program Manager

- Owned & launched Nokia Delivery Platform (NDP) by defining vision, scope, product roadmap & aligning these with Project Management Office (PMO) business goals. Gained buy-in across multi-disciplinary PMO groups by effectively presenting growth opportunities & renewed capabilities.
- Co-ordinated monitoring and measurement of Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) and Return on Investment (ROI) by capturing relevant data and leveraging output to analyze program effectiveness.
- Drive alignment with different stakeholders for the software project planning and execution, reprioritize product backlog, and cascaded customer feedback loops to stakeholder teams.
- Researched target markets, identified and secured viable product expansion opportunities worth \$15M that exceeded annual OKRs & synchronized with vision/goals of larger Business Unit (BU) strategy.
- Developed feature set based on UX feedback, refined backlog by clarifying requirements and dependencies, sizing and estimating user stories to get the prioritized Product and Sprint backlogs.
- Used data-driven analytics to understand poor customer adoption of previous model. Deployed robust solution architecture that improved customer adoption metrics by 30% & revenues by \$4M YoY.
- Identified market opportunities and served as the key liaison between organizations and clients for requirements mapping; released Product Requirements Document to help stakeholders understand the scope/scale of business need; communicated status to client CxO/executive management.

### **Capgemini** – Bangalore, India Consultant Program Manager

Feb 2015 - Jan 2018

- Managed portfolio of 7 products for Fortune-500 clients in Cloud Implementation, Business Process & Risk Mitigation; owned entire Product Development Lifecycle & oversaw teams globally dispersed.
- Streamlined product backlog prioritization by negotiating with Client and Product teams; wrote, reviewed & signed off on User Stories; updated the Customer Journey Maps, User Personas after feedback reviews.
- Demonstrated strategic-thinking and problem-solving capabilities by collaborating cross-functionally across the org to bring focus, clarity, alignment to business requirements for 12 projects in 3 programs.
- Trained and mentored team on issue diagnosis & resolution; facilitated Sprint Retrospectives focusing on meeting client needs, thereby improving deliverable quality by 25% & CSAT score by 15 basis points.
- Conducted quantitative impact analysis for change requests, ensured release and resource readiness to meet CAB timelines by supporting the various stakeholder groups in the change control process.
- Analyzed and documented end-to-end training needs of varied cross-functional and multi-cultural teams and presented the results to management; managed delivery of various knowledge/certificate programs.

# Manhattan Associates – Bangalore, India

Nov 2011 - Aug 2014

Senior Technical Manager

- Spearheaded cross-functional, quality-control initiative and removed redundant content from across Manhattan products. Recaptured 800 GB of storage translating to \$40,000 in savings on cloud server.
- Analyzed requirements framework of warehouse product and served as liaison between developers & product. Reconciled differences between client's expectations and team understanding of requirements.
- Helped in product growth by consistently addressing gaps in requirements, met and exceeded quarterly OKRs by focusing on backlog items that reduced churn and improved customer engagement by 35%.
- Introduced flexibility in the WM project schedule to accommodate known risks, created risk mitigation strategy for build or merge fails and used collaborative approach to working with stakeholders.
- Researched customer's Body of Knowledge on CRM (Salesforce) and used data-driven analytics and KPIs to direct Pre-sales and Marketing on collaterals, white papers, e-content, mobile marketing scripts.

# **Tata Consultancy Services** – Concord, California & Chennai, India Assistant Systems Engineer

Jan 2005 - Feb 2009

- Offered strategic direction and mentored 6-member team that provided 24/7 migration support for JavaScript, Java/Hadoop-based bank applications and reduced application downtime to zero.
- Consulted with bank executives & led meetings across bank verticals to finalize Teradata requirements; analyzed legacy systems to forecast storage and performed qualitative health analysis of system data.
- Applied Lean Six Sigma principles and streamlined workflow for production systems. Weeded out resource wastage by paring call volume/routing which improved customer satisfaction increased by 40%.